Guide to the Alfred S. Roe Civil War Papers, 1862 - 1865, 1891-1892
Alfred S. Roe Civil War Papers, 1862 - 1865, 1891-1892
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Roe, Alfred S. (Alfred Seelye), 1844-1917.
1000-99
0.5
2
Alfred S. Roe served with Company A, Ninth New York Heavy Artillery, from January 1864 to June 1865. Roe was captured in the Battle of Monocacy, Maryland, July 9, 1864, and was imprisoned at Danville, Virginia, for nearly eight months. He then attended Wesleyan University, from which he graduated 1870.
This collection contains a first hand account of a Civil War soldier and prisoner. The manuscript narrative gives details of Alfred S. Roe's experience in the Army and in prison, his travels, fellow soldiers, officers, and their conversations. Included in box 2 are Alfred Roe's letters to his parents, brothers, sister, aunt and uncle, and dear friend. There is also correspondence to Alfred Roe's parents from fellow soldier H. Hill Wheeler when Alfred went missing and again when he (Wheeler) learns Alfred is a prisoner.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Purchased from Cedric L. Robinson Bookseller, Windsor, CT, in 1967.
Biographical Note
Alfred S. Roe was a 20-year-old schoolteacher in Middleville, Herkimer Co., New York when he enlisted in the war. He was the son of a Methodist minister. He served with Company A, Ninth New York Heavy Artillery, from January 1864 to June 1865. Roe was captured by Early's troops in the Battle of Monocacy, Maryland, July 9, 1864, and was imprisoned at Danville, Virginia, for nearly eight months. He then attended Wesleyan University, from which he graduated 1870. After graduating from Wesleyan, Alfred Roe went on to be principal of the high schools in Ashland, MA and Worcester, MA. He served as a representative in the Massachusetts Legislature and as a state senator. He also authored Histories of Rose, N.Y., Worcester in the Spanish War and edited Worcester Light and Worcester Magazine. He married Nora A. Metcalf of Ashland, MA on June 22, 1874, and they had four children.
Collection Overview
This collection contains a first hand account of a Civil War soldier and prisoner. The manuscript narrative gives details of Alfred S. Roe's experience in the Army and in prison, his travels, fellow soldiers, officers, and their conversations. Included in box 2 are Alfred Roe's letters to his parents, brothers, sister, aunt and uncle, and dear friend. There is also correspondence to Alfred Roe's parents from fellow soldier H. Hill Wheeler when Alfred went missing and again when he (Wheeler) learns Alfred is a prisoner.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Roe, Alfred S. (Alfred Seelye), 1844-1917.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni and alumnae.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Danville Prison.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; United States. Army. New York Heavy Artillery Regiment, 9th (1862-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives.; Monocacy, Battle of, Md., 1864.; Soldiers--New York (State)--Correspondence.; Wheeler, H. Hill.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Enlistment Rosters, Rose, New York, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript, Narrative of Service as a Private, Company A, Ninth New York Heavy Artillery, by Alfred Seelye Roe, 1865 June, 248 pgs. (Folder 2)
    See transcript in Box 1, Folder 3.
  - Typed Transcription of Narrative of Service as a Private by Alfred Seelye Roe, given by Kate Thornburg, Class of 2005 (Folder 3)
  - Dr. Dame, Episcopal Rector photograph (Folder 4)
  - In a Rebel Prison: Or Experiences in Danville, VA, by Alred S. Roe, Providence; Soldiers' and Sailors' Historical Society of Rhode Island, Personal Narratives: Fourth Series, No. 16, 1891 (Folder 5)
  - Richmond, Annapolis, and Home, by Alred S. Roe, Providence; Soldiers' and Sailors' Historical Society of Rhode Island, Personal Narratives: Fourth Series, No. 17, 1892 (Folder 6)
  - Two leters from Alfred S. Roe to his parents, February 9, 1864 and March ?, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letter from A.S. Roe to his Aunt & Uncle, March 16, 1864 (Folder 2)
  - Letter from A.S. Roe to his parents, May 11, 1864 (Folder 3)
  - Letter from A.S. Roe to his parents, brothers & sister, July 2, 1864 (Folder 4)
    See transcript in Box 2, Folder 11.
  - Letter from A.S. Roe to his Dear Friend Lawrence, July 2, 1864
    See transcript in Box 2, Folder 12.
  - Letter to A.S. Roe's father from fellow soldier H. Hill Wheeler, Jr., July 12, 1864, saying he was missing (Folder 5)
  - Letter from A.S. Roe to his parents when he was a prisoner, July 31, 1864 (Folder 6)
  - Letter from H.H. Wheeler to A.S. Roe's parents, September 8, 1864 (Folder 7)
  - U.S. Christian Commission, Report on A.S. Roe's Imprisonment to his family, Oct. 23, 1864 (Folder 8)
  - Letter from A.S. Roe to Aunt & Uncle, April 18, 1865 (Folder 9)
  - Three letters from A.S. Roe to his parents, May 1865, June 9, 1865, July 30, 1865 (Folder 10)
    See transcript of June 9 letter in Box 2, Folder 11.
  - Three typed transcripts of letters from A.S. Roe to his parents, July 2, 1864 (original in Box 2, Folder 4), July 31, 1864 (original in Box 2, Folder 6), June 9, 1865 (original in Box 2, Folder 10) (Folder 11)
  - Typed transcript letter from A.S. Roe to Dear Friend Lawrence, July 2, 1864 (original in Box 2, Folder 4) (Folder 12)